<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The horrid sin of man-catching. The second part or, Further discoveries and arguments to prove, that there is no Protestant-plot, and that the design of casting a plot upon them, by the suborned man-catchers, was antecedent to the first discovery of the Popish Plot : together with some further discoveries concerning M. Booth : humbly dedicated to the Right Honourable, the Earl of Shaftsbury.</title>
            <author>T. S.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 68 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58716</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S166</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7955</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11902839</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11902839</idno>
            <idno type="VID">50604</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58716)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 50604)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 509:31)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The horrid sin of man-catching. The second part or, Further discoveries and arguments to prove, that there is no Protestant-plot, and that the design of casting a plot upon them, by the suborned man-catchers, was antecedent to the first discovery of the Popish Plot : together with some further discoveries concerning M. Booth : humbly dedicated to the Right Honourable, the Earl of Shaftsbury.</title>
                  <author>T. S.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for H. Jones,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: T.S.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in University of Pennsylvania Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Booth, John, 17th cent.</term>
               <term>Popish Plot, 1678.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:50604:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50604:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE HORRID SIN OF Man-Catching.</p>
            <p>The SECOND PART.</p>
            <p>Or Further <hi>Diſcoveries</hi> and <hi>Arguments</hi> to prove, That there is no <hi>PROTESTANT-PLOT;</hi> And that the Deſign of Caſting a Plot upon them, by the Suborned <hi>Man-Catchers,</hi> was An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecedent to the firſt Diſcovery of the POPISH-PLOT.</p>
            <p>Together with ſome further <hi>Diſcoveries</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>M. BOOTH.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Humbly Dedicated to the Right Honourable, the</hi> EARL of <hi>SHAFTSB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RY.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>H. Jones,</hi> 1681.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:50604:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50604:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable, ANTHONY, EARL of SHAFTSBURY.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>SO Ancient is the Cuſtome of Dedicating Books to Perſons of the greateſt Worth and Eminence, whoſe ſhining Vertues diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>play themſelves with ſo much Illuſtrions Beauty, that like the radiant Beams of the Sun, they forceably Attract the Admiring Eyes of all Men, and create in them a Deſire of having their Names found in the Frontiſepiece of their Books; that we find it practiſed even by ſome of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired Penmen of the Sacred Scriptures; for St. <hi>Luke</hi> Dedicates his Hiſtory of the Life and Actions of our Bleſſed Saviour, and that of the <hi>Acts of the Apoſtles,</hi> to the moſt Excellent <hi>Theophilus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> being one of thoſe few that have adventured to ſtem the Stream, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed to be Virtuous, when to be Wicked and Debauch'd is in Faſhion; And that dare to be
<pb facs="tcp:50604:3"/>Loyal, when to be ſo, is the way to be accounted Diſloyal, and that dare Oppoſe the Ambitious Deſigns of a Malicious and Bloody Party; Toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with your <hi>Lordſhip's</hi> having Suffered ſo deeply by theſe <hi>Shams,</hi> is all the Apology I ſhall make for preſuming to lay theſe Lines at your <hi>Lordſhip's</hi> Feet.</p>
            <p>The Malice of your Enemies ſhall ſerve as a File to ſet off the Glory and Luſtre of your <hi>Lordſhip's</hi> Loyalty, and your Name ſhall Live when theirs is Dead, and ſhine in Splendour, when theirs, like a Blaze, is gone out in a Snuff, the remembrance of your Name ſhall be as the ſmell of a pleaſant Field, or the delightful fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grancy which comes from a Garden of Flowers, when the remembrance of theirs ſhall be nauſeous and offenſive.</p>
            <p>As the mighty <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> accepted a Cup of Water from the hand of a Peaſant, ſo your <hi>Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> will ſhew how great a Maſter you are in the Art of Condeſcention, by Accepting theſe poor Indeavours of, my <hi>Lord,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your</hi> Lordſhip's <hi>moſt Humble and Devoted Servant,</hi> T. S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:50604:3"/>
            <head>THE HORRID SIN OF Man-Catching. The SECOND PART.</head>
            <p>IN ſuch a ſhamming Age as this is, wherein ſhamming is become a Trade or Science, and the Workmen ſo Ingenious, that no ſooner is one Sham diſcover'd but a new one is contrived to ſham that, ſo that for theſe laſt three years there hath been nothing but ſham upon ſham, or rather one continued ſham in ſeveral diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſes; it will not be amiſs to Collect and gather toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all thoſe ſeveral Shams which have been carried on by the <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſince the Plot, wherein they have had a double aim; the firſt, to ſtifle the Noiſe of their own Plot; the ſecond, to ſham one upon the <hi>Proteſtants;</hi> thereby hoping to deſtroy a conſiderable number of thoſe by their ſecond, which they miſſed the deſtroying by their firſt Plot.</p>
            <p>The firſt Sham we find took air, was immediately upon the firſt diſcovery of the Plot, by Mr. <hi>Everard,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they ſo ordered the matter, that his diſcovery was rewarded with the <hi>Tower,</hi> whither the Sham follows him, and he is ſolicited to lay a Plot upon the <hi>Proteſtants;</hi> even ſo early was the Deſign laid to carry a Plot upon the <hi>Proteſtants.</hi> Sir <hi>John Robinſon</hi> told him, thoſe ſtories he had diſcovered, concerning the Plot, were but trifles,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:50604:4"/>and ſtarting-holes from the only point he had to urge againſt him. That unleſs he would confeſs other Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters againſt the Duke of <hi>Monmouth,</hi> he would Rack him the next day, and afterwards hang him.</p>
            <p>The next Sham wherein they indeavoured to lay not only a Plot to Deſtroy the King; but (that which I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not Write without horror) the real Murder of the beſt of Kings, our preſent Sovereign, whom God long pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, upon the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> was their procuring ſome to ſwear againſt one <hi>Clapool,</hi> that he ſhould ſay, he would Kill the King; whereby they got him ſecured in the <hi>Tower,</hi> that ſo if God had permitted that which he hath graciouſly prevented, <hi>viz.</hi> the Murder of our dread Sovereign, they had preſently laid it on the <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians;</hi> for ſay they, there is one in the <hi>Tower</hi> that threatned it.</p>
            <p>The third Sham was as they would have the reſt, if they could, a bloody one, <hi>viz.</hi> The Murder of Sir <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mondbury Godfrey,</hi> which was done immediately upon the diſcovery of the Plot, by Dr. <hi>Oates,</hi> and then a curſed Report ſpread abroad by thoſe Murderers, that he had Murdered himſelf, wherein they had a double Deſign; firſt to ſtifle the further Proſecution and Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of the Helliſh Popiſh Plot, firſt by taking out of his Pocket, when they Murdered him, the Depoſitions of Dr. <hi>Oates.</hi> Secondly, By an infallible preventing his being a Witneſs againſt <hi>Coleman,</hi> at his Tryal; who, had as ſome ſay, diſcovered ſuch things to him, which they found means to prevent his diſcovering to any other, by promiſing to procure him a Pardon. Thirdly, By diſcouraging all Juſtices of the Peace and other Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates from daring to meddle with it any more, for fear of undergoing the like fate. Their ſecond Deſign in this Murder, was, by the cunning contrivance of it, to inſinuate, that Sir <hi>Edmondbury Godfrey</hi> had been an Ill
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:50604:4"/>man, and had Conſpired, with other <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> to Forge a Plot againſt the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and hir'd Dr. <hi>Oates,</hi> to Swear it, thereby the better to bring about ſome curſed Contrivance of their own; but being dogged and haunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the horror of a guilty Conſcience, for unjuſtly laying ſuch Horrid Crimes to the Charge of the poor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> was forc'd to become his own Executioner.</p>
            <p>The fourth Sham was their indeavour to prevail with Captain <hi>Bury</hi> and Alderman <hi>Brook,</hi> to Swear the Plot upon the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> for which purpoſe, they were to draw up in Writing what they would have them Swear, and promiſed 500 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> for their Reward. Now although theſe great Offers were not imbraced by theſe men, yet ſince they efcap'd ſo well without Puniſhment, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to offer them to all with whom they had the leaſt hopes to prevail, until ſome or other would adventure to purchaſe this Gold at the price of Blood.</p>
            <p>The fifth Sham, was my Lord Treaſurer's taking <hi>Bedloe</hi> into his Cloſet, and by great Offers, tempting him to withdraw his Evidence concerning the <hi>Popiſh Plot.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſixth Sham, was that great Attempt of <hi>Reading</hi> to Corrupt Mr. <hi>Bedloe,</hi> by the offer of an Eſtate, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquiſh his Teſtimony as to the Lords in the <hi>Tower.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſeventh Sham, was that Traiterous Libel, call'd the <hi>Compendium,</hi> contrived by the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> to ſham the Plot, by relating the Circumſtances of the Tryals with ſo much brevity and partiality, that they leave out the moſt material things upon which the ſtrength of the Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence lay.</p>
            <p>The eighth Sham, was a Libel, called, <hi>The Hiſtory of the Plot,</hi> by <hi>Roger L'Eſtrange,</hi> together with his fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Diſcovery, wherein he labours hard at it, to ſhuffle in ſomething in proof of the pretended <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Plot, and to ſtifle the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Plot, by pretending to a further Diſcovery of it.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:50604:5"/>
            <p> The ninth Sham, was the ſending abroad whole Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giments of Pamphlets (for you muſt know a great part of their ſhamming Talent lies in Pamphletting) of divers natures, ſome ſeeming to claſh one againſt ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſome to rail againſt the <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Popiſh</hi> Plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, but yet all ingeniouſly fixed by the ſubtile contrivers to ſerve the great Deſign of ſhamming the <hi>Popiſh,</hi> and inſinuating a <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Plot.</p>
            <p>The tenth was that of <hi>Knox, Lane,</hi> and <hi>Osborn,</hi> being a ſubtile Contrivance, managed by the joynt conſent of the Lords in the <hi>Tower,</hi> as appears by Mr. <hi>Dangerfeild</hi>'s Narrative, wherein they were to prove, 1. A Contrivance between Mr. <hi>Bedloe</hi> and Dr. <hi>Oates,</hi> to Charge the Earl of <hi>Danby</hi> with Treaſon; 2. To Charge Dr. <hi>Oates</hi> with Sodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; in both which they indeavoured to ſtifle the Plot; firſt by charging both <hi>Oates</hi> and <hi>Bedloe</hi> with Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury in ſwearing falſly againſt the Lord Treaſurer; and ſo, by conſequence, all they had Sworn againſt others was falſe too. 2. If they fail'd in this, yet if they could prove the Sodomy, they would thereby render him ſuch a profligate Wretch, that his Teſtimony was not to be credited.</p>
            <p>The eleventh Sham, was that commonly called the <hi>Meal-Tub Plot,</hi> which becauſe it ſeems to be the very ſame Sham with that which is now on foot, and is ſo hugg'd by ſome, only the perſons who Act this Trage-Comedy, ſome of them are changed, but the Maſter Contrivers and the Deſign of the Play is the ſame; therefore I ſhall be the longer upon it.</p>
            <p>About the later end of <hi>March,</hi> 1679. One Mrs. <hi>White,</hi> a Priſoner in <hi>Newgate,</hi> and one who had been Convict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, was releaſed out of Priſon, by Mrs. <hi>Cellier,</hi> after which ſhe came ſeveral times to viſit Mr. <hi>Dangerfeild,</hi> then likewiſe a Priſoner there, whereby ſhe learned, that he was a <hi>Roman Catholick;</hi> and Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> inquiring of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:50604:5"/>her about the Priſoners in <hi>Newgate,</hi> if it were not poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to find out a man of Courage amongſt them, and one who would reform? upon which ſhe gave ſuch a high Character of Mr. <hi>Dangerfeild,</hi> that ſhe immediately, ſuppoſing him a man fit for their purpoſe, gives him a viſit, and after ſome ſhort diſcourſe of <hi>Newgate</hi>-Affairs, acquainted him, that ſhe had a Buſineſs of great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern for him to do, which if he would undertake, ſhe would procure his Liberty, and a great Reward; in a word, ſhe would make his Fortune; which he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking, ſhe got him diſcharged. The firſt thing they imploy him about, was to find out ſome way to Invali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date the Teſtimony of Mr. <hi>Bedloe,</hi> by the means of one <hi>Stroude,</hi> a Priſoner in the <hi>Kings-Bench</hi> (as he was like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, for he was no ſooner out of <hi>Newgate,</hi> but he was Arreſted and carried to the <hi>Counter</hi> for Debt, whence he was removed to the <hi>Kings Bench;</hi>) but this not ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding, to their wiſh, they got him out, however he was in the Gallery at <hi>Powis-houſe,</hi> by the Lady <hi>Powis,</hi> thanked and praiſed for his diligence about <hi>Stroud</hi>'s buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; promiſing upon her Honour, that ſhe would for his faithfulneſs make his Fortune, provided he would undertake the Management of other Buſineſs ſhe had to do; he promiſing he would, ſhe gave him a long and ſtrict Charge; firſt, to be ſtedfaſt in the Principles of his Religion: ſecondly, to go once a Week to Mr. <hi>Monſon,</hi> to Confeſſion, which he promiſed to do; this was about the <hi>6th.</hi> of <hi>June,</hi> 1679. and becauſe all things were not ready, and they were loth to loſe time, they im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed him for the preſent in getting out five or ſix Prieſts, that lay in the <hi>Gate-houſe;</hi> two or three whereof he got out: then he carried a Letter from the Counteſs of <hi>Powis</hi> to the Earl of <hi>Caſtlemain;</hi> upon the receiving and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſing this Letter, my Lord received him very kindly, promiſing to make his Fortune, if he would uſe his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:50604:6"/>to ſupport the <hi>Catholick Cauſe,</hi> as he ſhould be directed. Then his Lordſhip writ a Letter to the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs, in Anſwer to that which he brought from her, which he ſent by him, and he delivered it to the Counteſs, who calling Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> to her, opened it, and read it in Mr. <hi>Dangerfeild</hi>'s preſence; the Contents whereof was to this purpoſe:</p>
            <p>Madam, <hi>Juſt now I received yours, and will meet you at the</hi> Tower, <hi>to Morrow, at Ten a Clock: but this Fellow I like well, and though he be no Scholar, yet he may ſerve to Inſtruct the Youths, according as he ſhall be directed; and in ſo doing, I ſhall be eaſed of much ſuſpicion,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>By the Youths, you muſt underſtand the St. <hi>Omer</hi>'s Witneſſes, who were lodged at Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi>'s Houſe, and were Inſtructed once in two days by <hi>Caſtlemain,</hi> all the time of their being in Town; yet ſome of them wanted their Leſſons at the time of the Tryal of the five <hi>Jeſuits</hi> at the <hi>Old Bayly,</hi> and therefore were again Inſtructed; yet blockheads that they were, they did not acquit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſo well as was hop'd they would. Then the Counteſs adviſed Mr. <hi>Dangerfeild</hi> to burn all Papers whatſoever, after he had peruſed them; which he did, even to the very laſt, otherwiſe he had been able to have proved all he charges them with, by their own hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>writing. Shortly after this, Mr. <hi>Dangerfeild</hi> ſuſpecting that Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi>'s Maid took more notice of Affairs than was neceſſary, he told the Counteſs, he did not like her; ſo the Counteſs adviſed Mrs. <hi>Cellier,</hi> to turn her away, and take a Boy in her room, who would be more conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient for carrying Letters; which was preſently done. Then the Counteſs of <hi>Powis</hi> ſent him with a Letter, to one Mrs. <hi>Jane,</hi> (as ſhe called him) at one Mr. <hi>Webs,</hi> at <hi>Peterley</hi> in <hi>Buckinghamſhire,</hi> and confer with her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ſome weighty Buſineſs; this Mr. <hi>Web</hi> was himſelf preſent when the Counteſs put him upon going, and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:50604:6"/>adviſed him, leſt the cauſe of his going ſhould be diſcovered, to bring his Son-in-law with him when he came back; ſaying, he had deſigned to ſend him to <hi>France</hi> long ſince, and that this would not only be a good Excuſe for him, but very convenient for his Journey alſo: then the Counteſs did order one of the Grooms, to hire a Horſe for him, not that her Ladyſhip wanted Horſes, but leſt it ſhould be known that ſhe ſent him, and ſo he ſhould be diſcovered; then Mr. <hi>Web</hi> adviſed him to put the Pacquet he was to carry into the Saddle-skirts, that ſo if he were taken, the Horſe being a Hackney, he might come off, by denying the thing. When he came to <hi>Peterley,</hi> he delivered the Letter to Mrs. <hi>Web</hi> from her husband; which as ſoon as ſhe had read, ſhe deſired him to follow her, which he did through divers Rooms, and up and down ſeveral pair of Stairs, till ſhe brought him into a Chamber, where ſhe bid him ſit down, ſaying, ſhe would preſently ſend the Lady to him, but inſtead of a Woman, ſhe ſent in a Man, (a Popiſh Prieſt) who af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter greeting, acquainted him, that for the ſecurity of his perſon theſe dangerous times, he was forc'd to retire there, and uſe the Name of Mrs. <hi>Jane:</hi> then he told him, he muſt preſently Confeſs, and receive the Sacrament, to be true to the Cauſe. He told him he had been drinking on the Road, and was not in a condition, and pray'd it might be deferr'd till the Morrow: but, he told him, that muſt not be; he was well enough, and muſt do it then, for he was to be gone early in the Morning, which when he had done, he took his leave, till the Morrow. When being ready to come away, Mrs. <hi>Web</hi> carried him to Mrs. <hi>Jane</hi>'s Chamber, and left them together. Then he told Mr. <hi>Dangerfeild,</hi> he had ſate up all Night to An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer thoſe Letters; <hi>and that he would now conſider by what Method to proceed in the Plot againſt the</hi> Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, <hi>and that the ground-work of the whole thing was among
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:50604:7"/>thoſe Papers, which he was to bring to</hi> London. When he came to <hi>London,</hi> the Counteſs, and Mrs. <hi>Cellier,</hi> told him, they were under great fear, leſt the Papers ſhould have been diſcover'd, and when he had deliver'd the Papers to the Counteſs, ſhe opened and overlook'd them all, but took one, and read it to him, which was to this effect: <hi>(viz.) Good ſtore of Pamphlets muſt be writ, and ſpread about the Town againſt the</hi> Presbyterians; <hi>perſons muſt be imployed to go to</hi> Coffee-Houſes, <hi>and rail againſt the</hi> Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians, <hi>and if they meet with any that offer to contend, matter of Treaſon, or ſome ſuch thing may eaſily be laid to their charge, to have them ſecured; but there muſt be many perſons imployed in this work, and it will be great prudence, not to let them know one another, and to let none of them know more than his own part: he blamed them like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, for letting Mr.</hi> Dangerfield <hi>know ſo much as he did: but, ſaid he, I have bound him faſt enough; and beſides that, I have a better opinion of him than I had of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> (meaning <hi>Gifford the Prieſt.</hi>) <hi>Theſe are the People that muſt do the work, and you let them lie in Priſons and ſtarve; which makes me wonder at your great negligence in ſo conſiderable an Affair,</hi> &amp;c. The reſt were conceal'd from him, and preſently ſent to the Lords in the <hi>Tower,</hi> and afterwards to Mr. <hi>Nevel,</hi> to peruſe and alter, as he thought fit; for he was the chief Pen-man, and did all that ſort of drudgery for a long time, till Mr. <hi>Dangerfeild</hi> relieved him; firſt, by Tranſcribing divers Papers after him: ſecondly, by ſetting up for himſelf, in ſcribling of Pamphlets, to further the Cauſe. By this time the Tryal of the five Jeſuits came on, and Mr. <hi>Dangerfeild</hi> not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving time, as was deſigned, to Inſtruct the Witneſſes, the Lord <hi>Caſtlemain</hi> continued in that imployment himſelf, and gave to ſome, who had ſhort Memories, Breviates, or Leſſons; others he adviſed with, ſometimes at his own Lodgings, other times at <hi>Powis-houſe,</hi> and ſometimes
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:50604:7"/>at Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi>'s; this was as common among the Youth's, as going to School, and ſometimes when they had been ſcanning over their Parts, and miſtook, they would pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently cry, Oh, I am out, I muſt go to my Lord <hi>Caſtle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main,</hi> to be Inſtructed again. Then was Mr. <hi>Dangerfeild</hi> ordered to Attend on the Lord <hi>Caſtlemain</hi> at the Seſſions held at the <hi>Old-Bayly,</hi> the <hi>13th.</hi> and <hi>14th.</hi> of <hi>June;</hi> and the ſaid Lord deſired him to take care of the Youths, and keep them together, leſt the Rabble, out of inveterate hatred ſhould offer them any Injury. Then he was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered to get into Court, and take Notes of the Tryals; and when the Tryals were over, the Lady <hi>Powis</hi> read them, and then ſent him to her Lord, to the <hi>Tower,</hi> to whom he ſhewed the little imperfect Remarks he had taken: his Lordſhip ſeemed to like them well; and, to incourage him to be Induſtrious in other Buſineſs, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended him highly for this, and gave him far better incouragement than ever he had from his Lady, or any body elſe, and promiſed, upon his Honour, to make his Fortune, if he would be rul'd. Then the Lord <hi>Powis</hi> ſent him to the Lord <hi>Bellaſis,</hi> and the other three Lords, to ſhew them his Notes, or rather himſelf; he ſhewed them to all thoſe Lords; and they all deſired, they might be Printed, and gave Money towards it; one a <hi>Guinea,</hi> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Fifty Shillings, one half a <hi>Guinea,</hi> another Fifteen or Sixteen Shillings: when he returned to my Lord <hi>Powis,</hi> he told him what the other Lords had done, then he alſo contributed to it, and told him, the Lord <hi>Caſtle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main</hi> ſhould do the like; at the ſame time he told him, that ſome had been imployed by them, to take the whole Tryals, which was to be Printed by one <hi>Turner,</hi> a <hi>Popiſh Bookſeller</hi> in <hi>Holborn,</hi> and ordered him, to carry his Notes to be compared with his, and one intire Relation to be compoſed of the whole, which was the <hi>Compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium.</hi> The Lord <hi>Arundel,</hi> laying his hand upon his head,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:50604:8"/>promiſed he ſhould be well rewarded for all his diligence; and the Lord <hi>Powis</hi> asked, <hi>Whether he had a faculty of writing abuſively, and like a Satyriſt; and was Maſter of ſuch a Style as would look well in Print? for,</hi> ſays he, <hi>he, that Sot</hi> Nevel, <hi>is ſo very delatory, it is not to be indured; therefore if you dare undertake the Writing ſome ſound Pamphlets, it might be of great uſe.</hi> To which he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, He would do his beſt. Then the Lord <hi>Powis</hi> told him, Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> ſhould be allowed Ten Shillings <hi>per</hi> Week, to diet him, and his Lordſhip would allow him Three Pound <hi>per</hi> Week for his Expences in Buſineſs; and whatever more ſhould happen, he ſhould put it in a Bill, and ſend it to his Lordſhip, and it ſhould be forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with paid; all which was done as long as he ſerved them. About the <hi>18th.</hi> of <hi>June,</hi> the Counteſs ſent him with a Letter to the Lady <hi>Tukes</hi> Lodgings, in <hi>Scotland<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard;</hi> who was pleaſed to ſay, She liked him very well, and gave him two <hi>Guinea's;</hi> and demanded, If he durſt undertake a deſperate Enterprize? he ſaid, Yes. Then ſhe Wrote a Letter to the Counteſs, and gave it him, to carry to her. Then they imployed him to get <hi>Knox</hi> and <hi>Lane</hi> out of Priſon; which he found hard to do, but in the mean time he got Pen, Ink, and Paper, to be conveyed to them, upon which <hi>Lane</hi> writ a Letter to this purpoſe:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I will die before I will Comply with that Villain</hi> Oates; <hi>and if any good People will work my liberty, I will do the</hi> Catholicks <hi>the greateſt Service imaginable, by Diſcovering what I know of</hi> Oates. <hi>This is from the bottom of my heart, and what I will die with. So help me God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the Counteſs read this Letter, ſhe was tranſport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Joy, ſaying, <hi>Has God given us this unexpected help? well, we will uſe it to the beſt Advantage.</hi> And the pious Counteſs was the greater part of that day on her
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:50604:8"/>knees, to render Thanks to God for this new ſtrength ſhe ſuppoſed God had been pleaſed to bleſs their Cauſe with. (Oh horrid Prophanneſs, to make God the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of Perjury!) About the <hi>14th.</hi> of <hi>July</hi> he was ſent for by their Lordſhips to the <hi>Tower,</hi> where he received Orders to ſend <hi>Lane</hi> out of the way. Soon after this the Lords ordered him, by Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> to go to a Coffee-houſe; accordingly he went every Night to <hi>Farr</hi>'s Cof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fee-houſe, to inſinuate, that the Earl of <hi>Danby</hi> was privy to the Murder of Sir <hi>Edmondbury Godfrey;</hi> that he took part with the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> and was confederate with them, to ruin the <hi>Roman Catholicks;</hi> and ſuch like ſtuff. Then the Lady <hi>Powis</hi> ſent him a great number of Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets; among which was the <hi>Danby Reflections;</hi> and ordered he ſhould diſperſe them into all parts; which he did; ſome into the Country, to the Gentry there; others to little petty Coffee-houſes about Town, and ſome he drop'd in the Streets, and in all Houſes, where he could, ſo that he had like to have drop'd into <hi>Newgate</hi> again, for doing ſuch a Trick in an Eminent Citizen's houſe, which made him more cautious. Then the Lord <hi>Powis</hi> ordered him to attend on <hi>Dormer,</hi> a reputed Prieſt, and one that Writ Pamphlets, and frequented Coffee-houſes, to inſinuate a <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Plot. His Lordſhip alſo or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered him to Converſe with one <hi>Turner,</hi> his Lordſhip's Prieſt, Mr. <hi>Munſon,</hi> Mr. <hi>Kemeſh,</hi> and <hi>Nevel,</hi> and to follow their Directions in all things; then <hi>Nevel</hi> ſent him divers Papers, Pamphlets, and Letters, to Tranſcribe; among which were 40 Liſts of Names, each Liſt contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about 800 Names; at another time he received from <hi>Nevel</hi> 27 Letters, moſt of them written with <hi>Nevel</hi>'s own hand, to Tranſcribe with all ſpeed, and at the ſame time <hi>Nevel</hi> ſent as many more to the <hi>Tower,</hi> by Mrs. <hi>Ayry.</hi> Some of them Mr. <hi>Dangerfeild</hi> had to Tranſcribe were as follows:</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:50604:9"/>
                  <head>Letter I.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Sir,</salute>
                     <dateline>London.</dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>r Buſineſs goes on very well, and I hope yours does the ſame in the Country: I am Informed that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions will ſpeedily be Iſſued out: and it is ſaid, there is ſome alteration among our people.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſecond Letter;</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>My heart is good, but the body is not of ſtrength enough to do you ſervice; but I doubt not but my Prayers, for your good ſucceſs, may be as ſerviceable and prevalent as my perſon, were it again in its prime, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>To ſuch like purpoſes were the reſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Dowdwel</hi> and Mrs. <hi>Ayry</hi> uſed to carry ſuch Papers and Letters as concerned the Deſign, to the <hi>Gate-houſe,</hi> and other Priſons about Town, to have the Advice of, and Conſent of the Prieſts and <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> there; the Lord <hi>Powis</hi> (as Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> told Mr. <hi>Dangerfeild</hi>) refuſed to meddle in the thing, unleſs it were generally approv'd of, as it was ſoon after; for all that either ſaw or heard of it, agreed in opinion, that it was a very ſound Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivance. And perſons were to be imployed to carry theſe Letters and other Papers into all parts of <hi>England,</hi> and ſome way or other found to lodge them in the houſes of ſuch as were the moſt eminent of the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Party: Then others were to obtain Warrants upon other pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, to ſearch their Houſes, and get the Perſons com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, in whoſe Houſes they were found: this they hop'd would occaſion ſo much confuſion throughout the Nation, that at leaſt every one would be glad to ſave himſelf, and the <hi>Papiſts</hi> come off upon the ſame terms, as others did. The next time Mr. <hi>Dangerfeild</hi> went to the <hi>Tower,</hi> my Lord <hi>Powis</hi> told him that one Mr. <hi>Doyley</hi> had ſeen or heard of him the laſt time he was with his Lordſhip, and had ſaid, in the hearing of one of his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip's Servants, That if ever he ſhould ſee him there again, he would have him ſecured; wherefore his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip adviſed him to come no more there, but return to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:50604:9"/>
               <hi>Powis-houſe,</hi> and be careful of his buſineſs. Then he commanded him to go to Mr. <hi>Turner,</hi> his Lordſhip's Prieſt, and take Directions how to Write to Mr. <hi>Holder</hi> at <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> he being his R. H. Auditor: the Letters con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd, an Account of the whole Deſign, and were Writ by the Counteſſes own hand, moſt earneſtly deſiring his good advice, as being unwilling to do any thing without it, therefore prayed his ſpeedy Anſwer. This Packet was made up by Mr. <hi>Turner,</hi> and Superſcribed by Mr. <hi>Dangerfeild,</hi> by <hi>Turner</hi>'s directions; <hi>For Mr.</hi> Tho. Holder, <hi>at Monſieur</hi> Keneydays, <hi>Secretary to the</hi> Engliſh <hi>Reſident in</hi> Bruſſels. In one of which Letters, <hi>they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired Mr.</hi> Holder, <hi>to imploy ſome ingenious perſon there, to Cut and Ingrave the Impreſſions of divers Coats of Arms;</hi> the Patterns whereof had been taken in Wax, and were ſent over incloſed in the ſame Letters, being faſtned with other Wax to the Margent of it. Some time after, the Counteſs having received an Anſwer to this Packet, ſhewed Mr. <hi>Dangerfeild</hi> a Letter to this purpoſe:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If you had taken this courſe ſooner, much Innocent Blood might have been ſaved; but I doubt 'tis now too late; I fear the St.</hi> Omer<hi>'s Witneſſes being ſo baffled, as I hear they were, has much blaſted our Deſign; but yet, to my power, I will aſſiſt, and do adviſe you to go on.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Letters to the ſame purpoſe came at the ſame time to Mrs. <hi>Cellier,</hi> which ſhe ſhewed to Mr. <hi>Dangerfeild,</hi> highly applauding this Gentleman, for his great Wit and Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, ſaying, If it had not been for him the Lords in the <hi>Tower</hi> had not been now alive. Then my Lord <hi>Powis,</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding his adviſing Mr. <hi>Dangerfeild</hi> to come there no more, ſent for him, to come thither to him forthwith, but diſguiſed; and when he came there, he found my Lord <hi>Arundel</hi> with my Lord <hi>Powis;</hi> and after much other Diſcourſe, my Lord <hi>Arundel</hi> demanded of him, If he would do any thing to make his Fortune? he anſwered,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:50604:10"/>Yes; (although he thought he had done enough to do that already) well then, Will you venter to Kill the King, for a good Reward? At that Mr. <hi>Dangerfeild</hi> being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazed, his Countenance changing, he replyed, My Lord, I ſuppoſe your Lordſhip is but in jeſt. No, ſaid he, I am in earneſt; and repeated his Queſtion: he anſwered, That to ſerve them, he was willing to be the death of any man whatſoever, but the King and his Royal Highneſs: but ſtill he preſs'd it the third time; then Mr. <hi>Danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feild</hi> apprehending his Life in danger, if he ſhould abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely refuſe it, deſir'd time to conſider of it. Then my Lord <hi>Powis,</hi> who was preſent all the time, ſaid, No, no, my Lord <hi>Arundel</hi> does this only to try you: — And pray, my Lord <hi>Arundel,</hi> ſaid he, What is it worth, what would you give him for doing it? 'Tis worth, ſaid the Lord <hi>Arundel,</hi> 2000 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> No more, ſaid my Lord <hi>Powis?</hi> Piſh, away; If he will kill my Lord <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> he ſhall have 500 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> Mr. <hi>Dangerfeild</hi> inquired, Why they deſir'd my Lord <hi>Shaftsbury</hi>'s life, and how it might be obtained? they both replied, it was eaſie to be done; for, ſaid the Lord <hi>Powis,</hi> my Man <hi>Wood</hi> was there two nights ſince, upon pretence of an Errand; but his buſineſs was, to view the Houſe, and obſerve what convenience there was for making an Eſcape, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Fact done; that <hi>Wood</hi> found the thing ſo fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, that after he came back, he ſaid, he was very ſorry he was not provided to have done it then; and the reaſon, ſaid he, why we would be glad to have him out of the way, is, becauſe we take for granted, if we were rid of him, (as they were of Sir <hi>Edmond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury Godfrey,</hi>) we ſhould find it no hard matter, to bear down all the reſt of our Oppoſers; with much perſuaſion he promiſed to undertake the Murder of the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury;</hi> upon which my Lord <hi>Powis</hi> gave him Ten <hi>Guinea's</hi> in earneſt. The next day Mr. <hi>Dangerfeild</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:50604:10"/>went to wait on my Lord <hi>Caſtlemain,</hi> who being Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the <hi>Compendium,</hi> roſe up in a haſty poſture, and caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an angry look upon Mr. <hi>Dangerfeild,</hi> ſaid, Why were you ſo unwilling to do that which you were taken out of Priſon for; my Lord being in this paſſion, he preſently went down ſtairs, and returned to Mrs. <hi>Cellier,</hi> who adviſed him to go to Mr. <hi>Sharp,</hi> the Prieſt at <hi>Wild-houſe;</hi> (for then his Kettle had more need of ſcouring than ever) the next Morning he went, and Confeſs'd, and received the Sacrament; which when he had done, he offered to come away, but <hi>Sharp,</hi> who it ſeems had been informed of his refuſing to kill the King, would not ſuffer him to depart ſo, but told him he ought to do Penance, for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing to ſerve God in what the Scripture taught him was his Duty: he deſired to know, whether the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures taught him any ſuch thing, as to kill the King? he anſwered (like a Jeſuit) Yes, if he were firſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated and Condemned by the Church, and that if he hoped to eſcape Damnation for his refuſal, he muſt undergo the Penance he then injoyned him. After this he was ſent to wait on <hi>Gadbury,</hi> who with an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry Countenance ſaid, I admire at your Ingratitude, that when you could not propoſe to your ſelf any poſſible way of getting out of Priſon, had not the Charity of good People relieved you, that you ſhould refuſe to kill the King; nay when you might have done it too with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any manner of danger, as I find by Calculating your Nativity. After this Mr. <hi>Dangerfeild</hi> made two At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts on my Lord <hi>Shaftsbury</hi>'s life, but was diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in both. His next Imployment was to lodge thoſe Treaſonable Papers he had to get Tranſcribed, in Col. <hi>Manſel</hi>'s Chamber. Now I ſhall firſt prove, that this was really a Plot of the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and not a contrivance of <hi>Dangerfeild</hi>'s. Secondly, I ſhall prove it to be the very
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:50604:11"/>ſame with that wherewith my Lord <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> my Lord <hi>Howard</hi> and others are now Charg'd, only ſome Circumſtances of time, place and perſons changed; and this I ſhall do by comparing one with t'other. <hi>Firſt,</hi> That it was a Popiſh Contrivance is plain, if you conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi>'s getting him firſt out of <hi>Newgate,</hi> then turn'd over from the <hi>Counter</hi> to the <hi>Kings-bench,</hi> then Compounding his Debts of 700 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> and getting him out thence, all which came to a large ſum of Mony, and therefore was not parted with for nothing; all this ſhe acknowledges her ſelf in that ſcurrilous Pamphlet of her's, called, <hi>Malice defeated. Secondly,</hi> It appears from the whole Contrivance of it, being found in her houſe, hid in her Meal-Tub, which ſhe acknowledged before the Council. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> It appears by their getting his Nativity Calcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated by <hi>Gadbury,</hi> which <hi>Celliers</hi> and <hi>Gadbury</hi> both ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> It appears by the great familia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity between my Lady <hi>Powis</hi> and him, ſhe acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhe had ſeen him ſeveral times, and that once he told her of ſome Treaſonable Papers hid at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and that the Secretary refuſed to grant him a Warrant to ſearch for them, unleſs he would make Affidavit; and that he was then adviſed to make uſe of the Cuſtom-houſe Officers to ſearch for them. <hi>Fifthly,</hi> It appears by his frequent viſiting the Lords in the <hi>Tower,</hi> as appears by Mr. <hi>Dayly</hi>'s taking notice of it, together with ſeveral other Circumſtances to confirm it. <hi>Sixthly,</hi> It appears by Mr. <hi>Matthew Hopkinſon</hi>'s acknowledging he Subſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed a Liſt of Names, and a Letter, for Mr. <hi>Dangerfeild. Seventhly.</hi> It appears by the Depoſition of <hi>William Wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> that he had known Mr. <hi>Dangerfeild</hi> at <hi>Powis-houſe</hi> about two Months, and that he had ſeen him and Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> Write together very often; That he carried a Pacquet of Letters from Mr. <hi>Dangerfeild,</hi> and Mrs. <hi>Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier,</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:50604:11"/>to the Lady <hi>Powis,</hi> and that her Ladiſhip opened the Pacquet, and read ſome of them, and gave ſome of them to him the ſaid <hi>Woodman,</hi> to carry to <hi>Nevill</hi> in the <hi>Kings-bench;</hi> and that he carried Letters divers times between Mrs. <hi>Cellier,</hi> Mr. <hi>Dangerfeild,</hi> and <hi>Nevill. Eighthly,</hi> It appears by Mr. <hi>Dangerfeild</hi>'s being intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd to the Lord <hi>Peterborough,</hi> by Mrs. <hi>Cellier,</hi> in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the making a diſcovery of this pretended Plot, and by him to the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> and by the Duke to the King. <hi>Ninthly,</hi> It appears by the Lord <hi>Peterborough</hi>'s acknowledging, that Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> deſired him to get a Warrant to ſearch for theſe Papers, ſaying, That if he would do ſo, all would be diſcovered, and that ſhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired this Warrant might be obtained without the King's knowledge. <hi>Tenthly,</hi> It appears by the Examination of <hi>Anne Blake,</hi> Servant to <hi>Cellier,</hi> who Depoſed upon Oath, before the Council, That her Miſtris gave her two Parcels of Papers, deſiring her to lay them up where they might not be diſcovered, and that accordingly ſhe laid one Parcel behind the Pewter in the Kitchin, and hid the other in the Tub of Meal. <hi>Laſtly,</hi> It appears as plain as the Sun, by Mrs. <hi>Celliers</hi> ſending to him, after his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſent to <hi>Newgate,</hi> 20 <hi>Shillings</hi> in Silver and a <hi>Guinea,</hi> and two Books of Account, telling him, by her Maid, That her Life was in his hands, and therefore deſired him to follow her Directions in a little Note ſhe ſent him, which was this: <hi>I have ſaid, you were taken into my Houſe, to get in bad Debts. They'l bring me to</hi> L. S. <hi>They will ask me, Who incouraged me to go to him? I will ſay, You did: It cannot worſt you.</hi> And in another little Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per thus: <hi>I never change.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet behold their Impudence, ſhe, before the Council, denied all this; but when the Notes were ſhown her, ſhe acknowledged it. Now, if they will be ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:50604:12"/>as to deny that which they knew could be prov'd againſt them by their own hand-writing, much more obſtinately may they deny thoſe things which they very well knew, the Papers that concerned them, were burned by Mr. <hi>Dangerfeild,</hi> according to their Directions. <hi>Secondly,</hi> I ſhall prove, That the Meal-Tub Plot is the very ſame with this wherewith my Lord <hi>Shaftsbury, Howard,</hi> and others are now charged with, which will appear, if you compare one with the other. Firſt, The forerunner or Forlorn-hope of that, was a numerous company of ſcurrilous Pamphlets, to prepare the way, by inſinuating, That there were ſome great Deſigns among the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> to diſturb the Government, which was in a little time diſcovered to be a Popiſh Brat, and by the good Providence of God was delivered before its time. Juſt ſo it was in this Plot, a numerous com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Pamphlets were diſpers'd about, to inſinuate ſome great Deſigns among the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw the Government, ſuch as <hi>Heraclitus,</hi> the <hi>Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vator, Thompſon</hi>'s <hi>Intelligence, Aſhinton</hi>'s blaſphemous Pamphlet, called <hi>The Presbyterian Creed and Pater-noſter,</hi> with abundance more. <hi>Secondly,</hi> It appears by their imploying the ſame perſons to diſperſe theſe Pamphlets, as were imployed to diſperſe the former, <hi>viz. Thompſon, Hindmarſh,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> It appears to be the ſame Plot, becauſe the ſame perſons are charged to be in the one as were charged to be in the other, as you will find, if you look into the Liſt in <hi>Dangerfeild</hi>'s Narrative. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> It's the ſame Plot, as will appear by the Nature and frame of it, which is exactly like the other, for they were then charged with a Deſign, to raiſe an Army to overthrow the Government, and reduce it to a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth; ſo they are charged now with the ſame thing, only that pretended Plot was ſaid to be upon His
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:50604:12"/>Majeſties being ſick at <hi>Windſor,</hi> and this upon the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of his Majeſties going to <hi>Oxford</hi> to Meet the Parliament. <hi>Fifthly</hi> It appears to be forged in the ſame Shop, becauſe it was generally reported among the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> a Week before my Lord <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> was appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended, that he would be taken up; nay, they had the impudence to Boaſt of it to ſome <hi>Proteſtants;</hi> For one Mr. <hi>Pulford,</hi> a Merchant, being at the Houſe of a <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt,</hi> a Week before my Lord was taken up, and having ſome Diſcourſe about the Plot, they ſaid, It would ſhortly appear to be a <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Plot, and my Lord <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> would ſpeedily be taken up for it. And one Mrs. <hi>Care,</hi> in the <hi>Strand,</hi> ſaid a Week before he was taken up, That my Lord <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> would ſhortly be taken up.</p>
            <p>The next Sham-Plot is that of <hi>Price,</hi> and <hi>Tasbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough;</hi> firſt to take off the Evidence of Mr. <hi>Dugdale,</hi> by promiſing him great Rewards and to procure him a Pardon for thoſe pretended Crimes wherewith he was falſly to accuſe himſelf, in ſwearing falſly againſt the <hi>Papiſts. Secondly,</hi> When they found he delaied them, and feared it was like to fare with them, as it did with <hi>Redding,</hi> they thought to be before-hand with him, and complain, that it was unjuſt, that the poor innocent <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> ſhould ſuffer ſo hardly, by the Evidence of ſuch Wretches, as would turn like a Door upon its Hinges, forward and backward, and for a Sum of Money, would deny what they had ſworn, and run away when they had done: but Mr. <hi>Dugdale</hi> foreſeeing this, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted ſeveral ſufficient perſons, from time to time, with the whole Intreague, who atteſting it before the Council, the Sham came to nothing, and they were juſtly rewarded for their contrivance.</p>
            <p>The next Sham was <hi>Cellier</hi>'s Pamphlet, called <hi>Malice defeated;</hi> whereby ſhe indeavoured (after ſhe got her
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:50604:13"/>Diſcharge, contrary to her own expectation, when ſhe ſaid her Life was in Mr. <hi>Dangerfeild</hi>'s hand, and this by an <hi>Ignoramus</hi> which we never heard of in <hi>Heraclitus,</hi> the <hi>Obſervator,</hi> or <hi>Thompſon</hi>'s Intelligence) indeavoured to perſuade the World, that there was nothing but Malice in her Charge, or in the Popiſh Plot, but a meer Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance.</p>
            <p>Another of their Shams was their ſending ſeveral perſons to the Houſes of ſeveral <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> in this City, to beg their Charitable Contribution, towards the Maintainance of Dr. <hi>Oates,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Bedloe,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending the King's Allowance was too little, but they were every where rejected; and it's well they were, for otherwiſe, it's not to be doubted, but the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> Good Works would have been brought to prove them Evil Doers.</p>
            <p>Their next Sham was, their perverting Mr. <hi>Blood,</hi> and prevailing with him to ſend a Treaſonable Letter to Dr. <hi>Oates,</hi> and then ordering ſome to Search and Rum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage the Doctor's Papers, hoping to find it there, and ſo to have proved him a Confederate with the <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians:</hi> but the wary Doctor, conſidering how many Trepans and Tricks the <hi>Papiſts</hi> uſed to ruin him, wiſely diſpatch'd it away immediately to Sir <hi>Joſeph William<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> then Secretary of State and a Member of the long Parliament then ſitting; which Letter Sir <hi>Joſeph Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liamſon</hi> afterwards produced in Council. And when all this fail'd, then their next Sham was to ſend one <hi>Lewis</hi> to the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> to deſire his Lordſhip would pleaſe to ſend by him to Dr. <hi>Oates</hi> ſome Directions of his own hand-writing, how to manage himſelf; but my Lord wiſely ſent this Decoy away with a flat Denial, well knowing, that malicious men may rack and ſtretch inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent words, till they make them ſpeak a quite contrary thing.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:50604:13"/>
            <p> Their next Sham was the prevailing with <hi>Simſon Tongue,</hi> to Swear that his Father, Dr. <hi>Oates,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loe,</hi> with ſome perſons of quality, contrived the Popiſh Plot; for young <hi>Tongue</hi> frequenting the Houſe of Mrs. <hi>Lane,</hi> about <hi>June,</hi> 1680. a Woman, that ow'd Dr. <hi>Oates</hi> a good turn for the Juſtice done upon her Son, <hi>John Lane,</hi> upon the Doctor's account: She, with a Popiſh Woman that lay in her houſe, by many Intreaties, and great Promiſes, perſuaded him to Swear, that his Father, <hi>Oates,</hi> and <hi>Bedloe,</hi> with ſome others, contrived the Plot, and finding thoſe great Offers had wrought ſome good In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations in him, they ſend for one Captain <hi>Ely,</hi> who came and conferred with him about it, and the next day they had a ſecond Meeting about it, and then <hi>Simſon</hi> ſhews him a Paper, the purport whereof was, to invali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date the Evidence of Dr. <hi>Oates,</hi> and that he and his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had contrived the Popiſh Plot. This Writing being under <hi>Tongue</hi>'s own hand, was depoſited in <hi>Ely</hi>'s hands, who aſſured <hi>Tongue,</hi> he would carry it to his Majeſty. But this being but a ſingle Cord, was not ſtrong enough, wherefore they reſolve to twiſt it, by finding out a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Witneſs. To this purpoſe they make an Eſſay upon one Mrs. <hi>Fitz-Gerald,</hi> a perſon at that time very low, both in Body and Purſe, and therefore, as they thought, the more likely to be Suborned, wherefore <hi>Ely</hi> ſent her a very loving Letter, Forty Shillings in Money, and great Promiſes of an able Phyſician, and other Kindneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes for the future, but without the leaſt intimation of what Deſign he had upon her. But preſently after <hi>Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> is ſent to treat with her, and he promiſes her God knows what, if ſhe would but Swear. In a ſhort time he gives her a ſecond Viſit, and brings with him Captain <hi>Ely,</hi> and one <hi>Choqueux,</hi> a Chyrurgion, and a <hi>French</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt, who was her Doctor, and very careful of her in
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:50604:14"/>her ſickneſs. They would have her Swear, there was no Plot, but what Dr. <hi>Tongue, Oates,</hi> and <hi>Bedloe,</hi> had made out of their own heads; ſhe told them, ſhe knew nothing of that matter: Yes, quoth <hi>Simſon,</hi> you do, and I have told the King of it at <hi>Windſor,</hi> and he is very de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to ſee you; and ſince you are ſo weak, that you cannot go to him, he will come to you ſomewhere here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>about, in a diſguiſe. But ſhe anſwered, 'Tis a folly to bring the King to me, for I know him not, and for that reaſon, if I had any thing to ſay, I would not be Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pan'd to diſcover it. When all this would not do, they indeavoured to Suborn one <hi>Iſaac Cooper,</hi> to Swear it, who if they could have gotten him to Swear, would have been the more credited, becauſe he was Dr. <hi>Tongue</hi>'s Clerk, but he was ſo honeſt, that notwithſtanding their large Promiſes, and noble Treats, he told them he had nothing to declare. This put them to a ſtand, but pluck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up their Spirits, they reſolve that young <hi>Tongue</hi> ſhall reveal the whole buſineſs to the King: but now he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to boggle, for fear his Father ſhould be hang'd, but <hi>Ely</hi> aſſured him, they would procure a Pardon for him. He being eaſily ſatisfied with this, the fore-mentioned Paper was diſpatch'd to his Majeſty, inclos'd in a Letter, wherein he promiſes to make great Diſcoveries, and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly ſolicites for his Majeſties Protection. And in another Letter to his Majeſty, dated <hi>Aug.</hi> 8. 1680. He ſays, That his Father and Dr. <hi>Oates</hi> correſponded with my Lord <hi>Wharton</hi> and the Earls of <hi>Eſſex</hi> and <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> and my Lord of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> was very forward in the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Plot, and ſent ſeveral Letters from <hi>London</hi> concerning it; That theſe Lords, the two Doctors convers'd with, and had aſſiſtance from, while they were forging the Plot. But unluckily it came at laſt to the ears of his Uncle, Captain <hi>John Tongue,</hi> who ſends for his hopeful Kinſman, and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:50604:14"/>laying before him the wickedneſs of his Project, <hi>Simſon</hi> falls on his knees, begs his pardon, and gave him a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantation under his own hand, wherein was contained an account of the whole Roguery. And now one would think here ſhould be an end of the Comedy, and that the Man and his Cauſe were ſtranded for ever, ſo that no Engine could bring him off thoſe Flats: for if he ſhould be ſo impudent to proſecute it any more, his own hand wherewith he had Subſcribed his Recantation, would confront his Evidence. But ſo deſperately hardned are theſe wretches, that they will ſtorm all Difficulties, nay Impoſſibilities, and in ſpite of Fate purſue their curſed Reſolutions. This Recantation had, it ſeems, taken air, and flown to his Majeſties ears, which <hi>Simſon</hi> under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, Addreſſes his Majeſty with two Letters, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, beſides other ſcandalous Lies againſt his Uncle, he tells his Majeſty, that his Uncle was very earneſt with him, to recant what he had given in concerning the Plot, and ſay he was hired to do it by the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> but yet he ſtood firm to his Tacklings, and did not give his Uncle a Recantation, tho' his Uncle pretended he had. <hi>Simſon</hi> after this, willing to get the Reward promiſed, applied himſelf firſt to Mrs. <hi>Cellier,</hi> then to truſty <hi>Hodge,</hi> who mainly applauded him, ſaying, he was upon a good De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, praying it might proſper. But being all brought before, and examined by the Council, ſo much of the Roguery was diſcovered, that <hi>Simſon</hi> was ſent to <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate. And</hi> Roger L'Eſtrange <hi>being willing to diſcover this Plot to the Nation, and to make the moſt of it, Print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a further Diſcovery of it, in a</hi> Dialogue, <hi>wherein he very elaborately proves it to be a Sham of the plaguy</hi> Presbyterians, <hi>and that it came out of their bottomleſs Belly to inſnare poor harmleſs</hi> Hodge, <hi>and the innocent</hi> Roman Catholicks.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:50604:15"/>
            <p> But by the way obſerve, that my Lord <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> was in this, as well as in all other of their Shams; And therefore I do Challenge thoſe that have any thing to ſay againſt the Legality of the Grand Juries Proceeding, to produce ſomething that looks like reaſon, why the Jury ſhould believe my Lord <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> to be more Guilty of this Plot, than he was of thoſe which were to have been Sworn againſt him by Mr. <hi>Dangerfeild, Simſon Tongue,</hi> and others, ſince the only difference that appears between them is, that they had the hap to be diſcovered before they were come to maturity, and this was not.</p>
            <p>The next Sham we ſhall take notice of ſhall be that of <hi>Booth</hi> and <hi>Bains,</hi> as you find it in <hi>Wilkinſon</hi>'s Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation. Captain <hi>Henry Wilkinſon,</hi> being by his good Service and bad Fortune, reduced to a low condition, and being now a Priſoner in the <hi>Kings-bench</hi> Priſon, one Mr. <hi>Bains,</hi> upon <hi>Octob.</hi> 8. 1681. came to him, and after many Expreſſions of kindneſs, told him, That he muſt needs know much of the Earl of <hi>Sbaftsbury</hi>'s Deſigns againſt the King, and would do well to diſcover it to him; and he would help him to a Pardon, and a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Reward. But the Captain told him, he knew nothing againſt my Lord: <hi>Bains</hi> leaves him. But on the <hi>11th</hi> of <hi>October,</hi> comes one Mr. <hi>Booth,</hi> who told him, if he would diſcover what he knew of the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi>'s Deſigns to ſet up a Common-wealth, he ſhould have 500 <hi>
                  <abbr>l.</abbr> per Annum</hi> ſettled on him and his Heirs, or (if he liked that better) 1000 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> in ready Money; but the Captain refuſed that great Bribe, and returned the ſame Anſwer as he had done to <hi>Bains.</hi> But when they had broke the Ice, they would not be ſo put off, but the next day they ſet upon him again, and to great Promiſes, add great Treats; and when this fail'd,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:50604:15"/>like the firſt Seducer, they ſet upon his Wife, intreating her to perſuade her Husband; but when this and many other Contrivances would not bring him to their Bow, they had him up to the King and Council, where <hi>Booth</hi> Swore High Treaſon againſt him, That he was to be Captain of a Troop of Horſe of Fifty, in this new Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice againſt his Majeſty, and he the ſaid <hi>Booth</hi> was Liſted under him.</p>
            <p>This <hi>John Booth</hi> is one that hath been Condemned for Clipping and Coining, beſides Murder; and about this time that he pretends he was Liſted under Captain <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinſon,</hi> it is very plain, that he was buſying himſelf about things of a different nature, not much for his cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit; for being about that time to go with Captain <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinſon</hi> to <hi>Carolina,</hi> and being unwilling to go empty, he comes to one Mr. <hi>Halford,</hi> a Mercer, with a pretended Letter from the Lady <hi>Ogle,</hi> to Buy her ſeveral Rich flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er'd Silks, and other Rich Things, to the value of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Two and Three Hundred Pounds, and to ſweeten him the more, brings Mr. <hi>Halford</hi>'s Brother with him, and tells him, that for his Brother's ſake he had a great kindneſs for him, and had rather he ſhould take his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney than another man, and told him, that he expected ſhortly to be Steward to the Duke of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> and that then he would do him great Kindneſſes. Mr. <hi>Halford</hi> replyed, Sir, I have not all theſe Goods you ſpeak of, but if you pleaſe, I will get them for you. Pray do, ſays <hi>Booth;</hi> accordingly the Goods were gotten: and at the time appointed, he came to look on them, and liked them well: But, Sir, ſaid Mr. <hi>Halford,</hi> theſe Goods comes to a great deal of Money, and I am but a young Beginner, and therefore cannot Truſt ſo much at once; but if you will have them, and Pay me ready Mony for them, you ſhall have them Cheaper than you will
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:50604:16"/>Buy them any where elſe. Sir, ſaid he, I will come and Pay you ready Money for them, but never came near him again.</p>
            <p>After the ſame manner he went to Mr. <hi>John Ridgies,</hi> an Upholſter, for ſeveral Rich Goods, but he alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing to Truſt him, he heard no more of his Chapman. Now it's more than probable, that the miſſing this Booty, he thought to get of Mr. <hi>Halford,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Ridgies,</hi> and it's like of ſome others, was the occaſion that he went not aboard according to his promiſe, to Captain <hi>Wilkin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> for he thought it a vain thing, to go to <hi>Carolina,</hi> being thus unhappily diſappointed of his <hi>Cargo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After this, being in great diſtreſs for a New Sute, he goes to a Tailor in <hi>Field-lane,</hi> and deſired him to make him a Suit, which he did, and carried it home to his Lodging, he lodging then at <hi>Bains</hi>'s, the Suit was tried on, and it pleaſed him wonderful well, Ay and 'twas mighty Cheap; But, ſaid <hi>Booth,</hi> I am very ſorry that I am diſappointed of Money I was to have received yeſterday, ſo that I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not Pay you; but, pray Sir, be pleaſed to call within a day or two, and your Money ſhall be ready for you: but when he called for his Money, there was no ſuch Man, as <hi>Booth,</hi> Lodg'd there: and the poor man was really diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointed of his Money; but at laſt he is informed, that he might ſpeak with his Son, at a Chamber in the <hi>Temple,</hi> whither he goes, and with ſome difficulty, gets to the ſpeech of young <hi>Booth,</hi> who told him, That truly he was aſhamed to ſee him, becauſe his Father had been diſappointed of Money, ſo that he could not Pay him; but, to tell you the truth, continued he, my Father is in the Countrey (although he was at that time a Priſoner in Mr. <hi>Weaver</hi>'s Houſe in the <hi>Rules</hi>) and ſince he went down, he did ſend up 5 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> for you, but a Friend of mine, being in great diſtreſs for Money, I lent it him, but you
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:50604:16"/>ſhall be ſure to have your Money very ſpeedily, which was all the ſatisfaction he could get.</p>
            <p>But thoſe great Attempts, ſince the diſcovery of the Plot, to caſt a Plot on the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> were not the firſt, but it begun much ſooner, <hi>viz.</hi> in the Year 1661. as we have an Account of it by Captain <hi>Yarranton:</hi> It was after this manner. There were ſeveral Letters forged, and delivered by Sir <hi>John P</hi> — to one <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard N</hi>— his Neighbour, to carry to one <hi>Cole</hi> of <hi>Martly,</hi> about four Miles from <hi>Worceſter,</hi> who accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Directions, delivered a Pacquet of Letters to one <hi>Churne</hi> of <hi>Witchinford;</hi> which Pacquet of Letters was carried by <hi>Cole</hi> and <hi>Churne</hi> unto Sir <hi>John P</hi>— (from whom it firſt came.) And before him <hi>Churne</hi> makes <hi>Affidavit,</hi> That going early in the Morning to his La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, he ſtruck his Bill upon a Hedge, to cut a Thorne, and by and by, on the other ſide of the Hedge, he eſpi'd a <hi>Scotch</hi>-Pedlar, putting up Letters haſtily into his Pack, and being affrighted (as he ſuppos'd) he left that Packet behind in the Ditch, and went down a Lane leading to Col. <hi>John Birch</hi> his Houſe.</p>
            <p>This Oath being made, and the Packet delivered, and opened, it preſently appeared, that there was a Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy on foot to ſtir up a Rebellion in the Kingdom, and to raiſe an Army for that purpoſe; and that Captain <hi>Andrew Yarranton</hi> was to Command a Party in thoſe Parts; for which purpoſe there were ſeveral Letters di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to him from ſome Miniſters, and others, particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly one from Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> intimating, that he had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided a conſiderable body of Men well Arm'd, which would be in readineſs againſt the time appointed. Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from Mr. <hi>Sparry,</hi> the then Miniſter of <hi>Martly,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timating that he had order'd him 500 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> which was lodg'd in a Friend's hand, and ſhould be ready for him when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:50604:17"/>he ſent for it, (but yet the perſon in whoſe hands it was, is not nam'd.) Several other Letters and Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Papers were pretended to be in that Packet; upon which the <hi>Militia</hi> of that County was raiſed, and the City of <hi>Worceſter</hi> was that Night filled with Horſe and Foot, and the next Morning, by Two of the Clock, an Officer with a Troop were ſent to apprehend Mr. <hi>Yar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranton,</hi> and bring him to <hi>Worceſter,</hi> and the ſame day ſome Scores more were apprehended and ſent to ſeveral places of confinement; but after Ten days the Sham began to appear, ſo that the Trained Bands would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue no longer: And upon their departure the Deputy-Lieutenants diſcharged all the Priſoners, except Dr. <hi>Jack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> Mr. <hi>Sparry,</hi> the two <hi>Oſlands,</hi> Capt. <hi>Wells,</hi> and <hi>Yar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranton,</hi> who were ordered to be kept cloſe Priſoners in ſeveral Chambers of the <hi>George Inn,</hi> and the Trained Bands being gone home, the Clergy provided about 60 Foot-Souldiers, which they Arm'd and Paid, to Guard the Criminals that remain'd in Cuſtody; this was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called the <hi>Clergy Band,</hi> and whilſt they continued in Guard, one <hi>Roger Waldern,</hi> a poor Old Man, came to <hi>Worceſter,</hi> to enquire after the Welfare of Mr. <hi>Henry Oſland,</hi> his Miniſter, and ſpeaking with one of thoſe Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, the Souldier liberally charged Mr. <hi>Oſland</hi> with being a Traytor, a Rebel, and a Plotter againſt the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment: He replied, Mr. <hi>Oſland</hi> was an honeſt and peaceable man, and he could never believe him to be guilty of Plotting againſt the Government. Upon this the Church-militant-man laid hold of him in great wrath, and carried him to the Court of Guard, where he was ty'd Neck and Heels together, and Charged with having a hand in this pretended <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Plot, threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with ſevere Uſage, unleſs he would make a Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: all this the Old Man bore with patience, anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:50604:17"/>never a word, which ſo inraged this man in Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, who Commanded the Guard, that he commanded lighted Matches to be put between his Fingers, and burnt them to the very Bone, thereby to force from him a Confeſſion of a <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Plot. And at the ſame time this Sham was carried on in ſeveral other Counties. For there came one Evening to the Houſe of Mr <hi>Martin,</hi> Town-Clark of <hi>Oxford,</hi> a Stranger with a Letter, who had no ſooner delivered it, but he withdrew, and went his way; when Mr. <hi>Martin</hi> had open'd and read the Letter, he prudently carried it immediately to the Mayor, for had he delayed it a day or two, it might have been found upon him, and then <hi>Oxford</hi> might have been as full of Plotters and Priſoners as <hi>Worceſter</hi> was. The Copy of this Memorable Letter is here inſerted, word for word.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Mr. <hi>Martin,</hi>
                     </salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Pray you warn all theſe Men, to be all in their Arms, upon <hi>Wedneſday</hi> next, in the Night; you know already where they muſt meet. There will come into <hi>Oxford</hi> Two Hundred Men, all in their Arms: you know who doth Command them. Dr. <hi>Greenwood</hi> has ſent to Mr. <hi>Combs</hi> the Barber, to get his Party of <hi>Scholars</hi> ready that Night; and I have ſent to Mr. <hi>Hickman,</hi> to get his Men ready at the ſame time; and Dr. <hi>Owen</hi> has ſent to Mr. <hi>Fogge,</hi> to get his Men ready at the ſame time; and Dr. <hi>Gawen</hi> has ſent to Mr. <hi>Duke,</hi> the Barber, to get his Men ready at the ſame time; and I have ſent to Mr. <hi>Corniſh,</hi> to get his Men ready at the ſame time; and I have ſent to Mr. <hi>Connaught,</hi> to get his Men ready; and all the Scholars are to meet in Dr. <hi>Rogers</hi> Garden: And I pray ſend the <hi>Blunderbuſſes</hi> thither, for I intend to be there my ſelf. And I pray give the Bearer hereof Five Pound out of the Stock: And I
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:50604:18"/>pray you remember me to the Six Men unnam'd. Five Counties are to riſe that Night, without fail: I need Write no more to you. The Word is, <hi>God is the Word;</hi> and I pray tell them all ſo.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>In this Letter there was incloſed a Liſt of the Mens Names he was to warn, which were an Hundred and Ten in all. But by his prudent carrying this Letter and Liſt of Names to the Mayor, he ſpoiled the well laid Deſign, and it came to nothing in that County. And ſo it did at <hi>Worceſter,</hi> for the perſon who was imployed to carry the Packet of Sham-Letters from Sir <hi>J. P.</hi> to one <hi>Cole</hi> of <hi>Martly,</hi> acquaints his Brother, how he came by the ſaid Packet: His Brother, immediately upon this Diſcovery, repairs to Mrs. <hi>Yarranton</hi> and informs her of it. She goes to <hi>Worceſter,</hi> and, with ſome difficulty, got a Letter delivered to her Husband, wherein ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated the whole Matter. Mr. <hi>Yarranton</hi> being thus let into the knowledge of this malicious Deſign, ordered Six Actions, to be immediately entered againſt ſome of thoſe perſons that brought him to Priſon. At laſt he was brought before the Lord Lieutenant, and ſix of his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties; Mr. <hi>Yarranton</hi> deſired the doors might be ſet open, for his Witneſſes to come in. He prayed alſo, that he might have Pen, Ink, and Paper, and he would Write down the whole Matter, for Words might be wreſted to other Intents than they are ſpoken. This was a while debated, but being ſo reaſonable, it could not be denied. But no ſooner did Mr. <hi>Yarranton</hi> begin to Write, but the Lord Lieutenant, and Sir <hi>J. P.</hi> leſt the Room, and went down the back ſtairs, and after them followed all the Deputy Lieutenants, except <abbr>Eſq</abbr> 
               <hi>Holt,</hi> who told Mr. <hi>Yarranton,</hi> That he was ſorry with all his heart, to ſee ſuch things practiſed to the diſturbance of honeſt
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:50604:18"/>Men, and the diſhonour of the Government. Then Mr. <hi>Yar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranton</hi> demanded, of the Marſhal what he had now to ſay to him further? He anſwered, All he had to ſay, was, to requeſt, That he would not trouble him, for holding him ſo long in reſtraint, for as much as he was a Poor Man, and had many Children, and did only follow the Orders of his Superiors: Mr. <hi>Yarranton</hi> told him, he did freely forgive him. Now although this Sham did not anſwer the deſire and expectation of the Contrivers in reference to the particular perſons that were accuſed, yet it did in general. For by this means they poſſeſs the King and Parliament, that it was abſolutely neceſſary to make ſome ſevere Law againſt this reſtleſs ſort of men, who not contented with the King's gracious Pardon, were always Plotting to diſturb the Government. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when the Parliament met on the <hi>20th.</hi> of <hi>Novem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> 1661. the King makes a Speech wherein are theſe words:</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="speech">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My Lords and Gentlemen,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Am ſorry to find that the general Temper and Affections of the Nation are not ſo well compoſed, as I hoped they would have been, after ſo ſignal Bleſſings of God Almighty upon us all, and after ſo great Indulgence and Condeſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions from me towards all Intereſts, there are many wicked Inſtruments ſtill as active as ever, who labour night and day to diſturb the Publick Peace, and to make all people Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of each other. It will be worthy of your Care and Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilance, to provide proper Remedies for Diſeaſes of that kind; and if you find new Diſeaſes, you muſt ſtudy new Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies. Let us not be diſcouraged; if we help one another, we ſhall, with God's bleſſing, maſter all our Diſſiculties. <hi>(And a little further,)</hi> You will find, whoever doth not love me, doth not you; and they who have no reverence for you, have little kindneſs for me.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:50604:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> From which laſt paſſage, we may conclude, That they are none of the King's Friends; nor are they of his mind, who in Word or Writing, do caſt Contempt on Parliaments.</p>
            <p>I ſhall conclude this brief Diſcourſe, with my hearty Deſire and Prayer to God, That he would pleaſe to Bleſs the King, and preſerve him from all his real Enemies, let them be called by what Name, or go under what Diſgui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſoever, and grant him a long, happy, and a quiet Reign. And in order hereunto, blaſt, and confound the <hi>Pope</hi> and all his Adherents in <hi>England,</hi> as well Maſque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raded, as open and profeſſed <hi>Papiſts. Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:50604:19"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
